{"tossups": [{"question": "This monarch names the North American theatre of the Nine Years' War, a conflict ended by the 1701 Treaty of Ryswick. The Immortal Seven sent a request to this<em> stadtholder</em> to seize control of one kingdom. The Jacobites, who sought to restore James II, were defeated by this man's army at the Battle of the Boyne. The husband of Queen Mary was, for the point, which Dutch nobleman from the House of Orange who was bestowed the English throne during the Glorious Revolution?", "answer": "<b><u>William of Orange</u></b> (accept <b><u>William III</u></b>; prompt on \"William\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This building was wrapped in silver fabric by the artists Christo and Jeanne-Claude in commemoration of one nation's reunification. Marinus van der Lubbe [[LOO-buh]] set fire to this building, leading to a \"Decree\" effectively banning the Communist Party. Yevgeny Khaldei [[KAHL-day]] photographed a Red Army soldier hoisting the Soviet flag above this building during the Battle of Berlin. For the point, name this German parliamentary building which today houses the Bundestag [[BOON-deh-shtahg]].", "answer": "<b><u>Reichstag</u></b> [[RIKE-shtahg]] (accept <b><u>Reichstag</u></b> Fire Decree; accept <b><u>Bundestag</u> </b>before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Under this fixture is a chapel dedicated to the patron saint of one nation, Our Lady Revealed, who supposedly appeared before three fishermen near the Paraiba [[pah-RYE-bah]] river. This figure, built to combat \u201can advancing tide of Godlessness,\u201d had much of its funding raised through the Semana do Monumento. This Philipp Landowski-designed statue sits atop Corcovado Mountain. For the point, name this massive statue of Jesus in Rio de Janeiro.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Christ the Redeemer</u></b></em> (or <em><b><u>Cristo Redentor</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The Naryshkin family supported this ruler at a young age, stopping his sister-regent Sophia from usurping power from him. This man's reign was followed by the so-called \"half-tsar,\" Alexander Menshikov, who dominated the reign of Catherine I. His tall stature and thick accent led to this tsar being easily recognized during his incognito \"Grand Embassy\" of Europe. The Empire of Russia was modernized by, for the point, what \"Great\" tsar?", "answer": "<b><u>Peter</u></b> I (or <b><u>Peter</u></b> the Great; accept <b><u>Pyotr</u></b> Vel\u00edkiy; or <b><u>Pyotr</u></b> Pyervyy)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A young Aaron Burr Sr. served as president of this institution following a dogmatic break from \"Old Side\" Presbyterians. Minister Jonathan Dickinson served as the first president of this institution following his expulsion from the synod of Philadelphia. British forces manned the \"Big Cannon\" while defending this university's Nassau Hall during a 1777 Revolutionary War battle. Woodrow Wilson served as president of, for the point, what Ivy League school northeast of Trenton?", "answer": "<b><u>Princeton</u></b> University (accept <b><u>College of New Jersey</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A self-taught weapon designer from this nation, Aimo Lahti, created the anti-tank \"Elephant Gun,\" though it proved unable to penetrate T-34s. To prevent the USSR from using radio-controlled explosives, this nation's military played four months of non-stop polka during the Continuation War. This nation built a ring of fortifications known as the Mannerheim Line to defend the Karelian Isthmus. The Winter War was fought against the Soviets by, for the point, what Scandinavian nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Finland</u></b> (or <b><u>Suomen</u></b> tasavalta; accept <b><u>Suomi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this year, much of the Jewish population of Granada was massacred following a plan by the Jewish vizier Joseph ibn Naghrela to betray the city to a rival<em> taifa</em> [[tah-EE-fah]]. In this year, the Earl of Orkney provided shelter to the Norwegians following the loss at Stamford Bridge and death of Harald Hardrada at the hands of Harold Godwinson. The Battle of Hastings led to William the Conqueror seizing the English throne in, for the point, what year?", "answer": "<b><u>1066</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "2007 riots in this city resulted from Muslim Imams calling for the death of writer Taslima Nasrin. Outside this city in the suburb of Barrackpore, the<em> sepoy</em> Mangal Pandey openly declared he would rebel against the British Raj due to the use of pig fat to grease cartridges. In this city, the Nawab of Bengal supposedly stuffed 140 prisoners of war in the tiny dungeon of Fort William. The Hooghly River runs through, for the point, what East Indian city with an infamous \"Black Hole\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Calcutta</u></b> (or <b><u>Kolkata</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was able to transition from civil servitude to composition full-time after the wealthy patron Nadezhda [[nah-DESH-dah]] Von Meck sponsored him on the condition that they never meet in person. This composer wrote both the music and libretto to his opera,<em> The Oprichnik</em>. Inspired by his nation's victory at Borodino over Napoleon to write one composition, this composer implemented the sound of cannon fire at its climax. For the point, name this Russian composer of<em> The 1812 Overture</em> and<em> Swan Lake</em>.", "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich <b><u>Tchaikovsky</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Following this event, a politician had to be found in the wilderness of Mount Marcy to be sworn in as president. African-American bystander James Parker halted a third shot during this event, which occurred in the Temple of Music. At the Pan-American Expo, an anarchist hid a revolver in a bandaged arm to perpetrate this violent event. Leon Czolgosz [[CHOHL-gosh]] committed, for the point, what violent act which resulted in the succession of Theodore Roosevelt as president of the U.S.?", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of William <b><u>McKinley</u></b> (accept descriptive answers involving the killing or shooting of William <b><u>McKinley</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A speech by this woman drew contemporary scrutiny after editor Francis Gage changed the script to imitate the Southern slave dialect despite this woman being from Ulster County, New York. This woman, who attempted to earn freedmen their \"forty acres and a mule,\" was the first Black woman to win a case against a white man. The \"Ain't I a Woman\" speech was given by, for the point, which 19th century Black and women's rights activist?", "answer": "Sojourner <b><u>Truth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The duties of knighthood lead a mythical figure from this nation, Owain, to lose his love, \"The Lady of the Fountain.\" The Celtic goddess of horses, Epona, is sometimes equated to this nation's mythic queen Rhiannon [[ree-AH-non]]. Bran the Blessed appears in a mythic cycle from this nation, attacking neighboring Ireland in an attempt to free his sister, Branwen. The<em> Mabinogion</em> [[MAH-bih-NOH-gee-un]] is a collection of myths from, for the point, which British substituent nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Wales</u></b> (accept <b><u>Welsh</u></b> Mythology; accept <b><u>Cymru</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, officer Nathan George Evans had a military aide carry a barrel of whiskey on his back. Early skirmishing in this battle occurred at Blackburn's Ford, leading P.G.T. Beauregard to send a telegraph to Joseph E. Johnston asking for reinforcements. Shortly before being wounded at this battle, Barnard Bee coined the nickname \"Stonewall\" for Thomas Jackson. For the point, name this first major battle of the Civil War, a Virginia engagement sometimes known as the Battle of Manassas.", "answer": "First Battle of <b><u>Bull Run</u></b> (accept First Battle of <b><u>Manassas</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One book by this man, which is dedicated to Paul III, was published with a forward claiming it was only meant to make mathematical predictions. This author of<em> On the</em> <em>Revolutions of the Heavenly Spheres</em> claimed that objects orbit in perfect circles. This man's namesake revolution led to the replacement of Ptolemy's geocentric model of the universe. For the point, name this Polish astronomer who promoted heliocentrism.", "answer": "Nicolaus <b><u>Copernicus</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Copernican</u></b> Revolution; accept Miko\u0142aj <b><u>Kopernik</u></b>; or Niclas <b><u>Koppernigk</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Protests of this legislation included the hanging of effigies of Massachusetts governor Andrew Oliver and of Martin Howard, who had promoted this legislation in \"A Colonist's Defence of Taxation.\u201d This legislation was introduced by George Grenville and inspired protests of \"taxation without representation.\" For the point, name this 1765 act that required playing cards and newspapers sold in the American colonies to be printed on paper from London.", "answer": "<b><u>Stamp</u></b> Act of 1765 (accept <b><u>Duties</u></b> in American Colonies Act 1765)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A<em> Wali</em> from this city named Husayn Pasha ibn Makki failed to prevent a Bedouin raid of<em> hajj</em> pilgrims. A type of high-quality steel named for this city had its method of production lost to modern smiths. The assassination of Uthman during the First Fitna and the rise of the Umayyads led to this city becoming the Caliphate's capital until the Abbasids moved it to Baghdad. For the point, name this modern capital of Syria.", "answer": "<b><u>Damascus</u></b> (accept <b><u>Dima</u><u>\u0161</u><u>q</u></b>; or <b><u>Darmswq</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During the Cultural Revolution in China, musical works of this form were highly edited by Jiang Qing [[CHING] and her staff of composers. Kim Jong-il published a treatise written specifically about this musical style. Musicologists suggest that Mozart's three great works in this style are subtle commentaries on society, as were the works of Verdi and Wagner [[VAHG-nur]]. For the point, name this genre of theatrical music exemplified by<em> The</em> <em>Marriage of Figaro</em> and<em> Nixon in China</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Opera</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This person is worshipped as a divine figure by the Yaohnanen [[yow-YAH-nen]] tribe, a cargo cult who venerate a photo depicting his 2007 visit to Vanuatu. This man, who was smuggled out of Greece as an infant in a fruit box, adopted his uncle's last name of Mountbatten due to anti-German sentiment in England. This man's funeral was held in April of 2021 in St. George's Chapel at Windsor Castle. For the point, name this man who held the title Duke of Edinburgh, the consort of Queen Elizabeth II.", "answer": "Prince <b><u>Philip</u></b>, Duke of Edinburgh (or <b><u>Philip</u></b> Mountbatten)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An Upton Sinclair work titled solely for this commodity tells the story of the Ross family, who become wealthy due to finding this resource on the Watkins's Ranch. In the 1940s, the method of \"Hydraulic Fracturing\" was introduced to acquire this resource. A \"spill\" of this product by the BP<em> Deepwater Horizon</em> led to devastation in the Gulf of Mexico. The breakup of John D. Rockefeller's company in, for the point, what industry led to subsidiaries like Exxon and Chevron?", "answer": "<b><u>Oil</u></b> (accept crude <b><u>oil</u></b> or <b><u>petrol</u></b>eum; prompt on \"gas\" alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city's Armenian Quarter was temporarily emptied following Justinian the Great's Monophysite [[muh-NAH-fih-site]] persecutions. While ruling a kingdom named for this city, Godfrey of Bouillon [[bwee-YOHN]] adopted the titles of<em> princeps</em> [[PRIN-seps]] and \"Defender of the Holy Sepulchre\" [[SEH-pul-ker]]. The success of the Maccabean revolt led to the cleansing of this city's Second Temple, inspiring the holiday of Hanukkah. The holiest city in Judaism is, for the point, what modern capital of Israel?", "answer": "<b><u>Jerusalem</u></b> (accept <b><u>Yerushal\u00e1yim</u></b>; or <b><u>al-Quds</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Jerusalem</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Structures on this island were toppled over in the decades following the arrival of Jacob Roggeveen [ROH-ge-veen], the first European to visit this island. A yearly race to retrieve an egg from a rock next to this island was an important part of this island\u2019s birdman cult. The still-undeciphered Rongorongo script was found on this island, which was annexed by Chile in 1888. For the point, name this island, home to sculpted heads called<em> moai</em> [[MOH-eye]].", "answer": "<b><u>Easter</u></b> Island (or <b><u>Rapa Nui</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The appearance of one of these objects prompted the abdication of Emperor Ruizong [[RWEE-ZONG]], passing the throne to Xuanzong [[ZHWAN-ZONG]]. Suetonius [[sweh-TOH-nee-us]] records one of these events occurring a few months after the death of Julius Caesar, believed by Roman citizenry to be his departing soul. One of these objects named Hale-Bopp precipitated Napoleon's 1812 invasion of Russia. Mark Twain's birth year and death year coincided with the arrival of, for the point, what type of astronomical phenomenon named for Edmund Halley?", "answer": "<b><u>Comet</u></b>s (accept Halley's <b><u>Comet</u></b>; accept <b><u>Comet</u></b> Hale-Bopp)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A downturn in this industry led to the Spitalfields [[SPIT-all-\"fields\"]] Riots in London's East End, where soldiers fired on weavers outside \"The Dolphin\" pub. Nylon was mass-produced in wartime Japan to replace a shortage of this product. The innovation of the Jacquard Loom led to resurgence of this cloth on the world market after it was overtaken by cotton. An ancient trade network traversing East Asia to Europe is named for, for the point, what luxury cloth?", "answer": "<b><u>Silk</u></b> (accept <b><u>Silk</u></b>worm; accept <b><u>Silk</u></b> Road)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man worked with Robert Livingstone to negotiate the Louisiana Purchase. Thomas Jefferson rejected this man and William Pinckney's renewal of Jay's Treaty. While governor, this man called out the state militia to put down Gabriel Prosser's rebellion in Virginia. This man was the last Democratic-Republican president before the rise of the Jacksonian Democrats. For the point, name this man who served as the fifth president of the United States.", "answer": "James <b><u>Monroe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In a work named for this field, ancient thinker Xenophon [[ZEN-uh-fun]] crafted a dialogue between Socrates and Ischomachus [[ISS-koh-MAHK-us]] in which they discuss farming techniques and how to manage a household. The first modern analysis in this field is considered Fernando Galiani's treatise<em> Della Moneta</em>. The mercantilism of Britain was criticized by Adam Smith in the<em> The Wealth of Nations</em>, a work in, for the point, what field concerning fiscal policy?", "answer": "<b><u>Economic</u></b>s (or <b><u>Economist</u></b>s; accept <em><b><u>Oeconomicus</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "In an effort to win concessions in the last days of this war, Deng Hua [[DUNG-HWAH]] led the Jincheng campaign. The landings at Green, Blue, and Red Beaches led to combined UN forces securing the port of Incheon during this war. Following the loss of his capital early in this war, Syngman Rhee relocated the government to Busan [[boo-SAHN]]. The Demilitarized Zone was established following, for the point, what East Asian conflict of the 1950s?", "answer": "<b><u>Korea</u></b>n War (accept <b><u>Choson</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Muralist Diego Rivera created a Marxist-inspired rendition of this city\u2019s<em> Industry</em>, depicting the River Rouge plant. The largest municipal bankruptcy in the U.S. occurred when this city declared Chapter Nine in 2013 largely due to the mass exodus of a million people. This city served as the historical center of the Ford Motor Company. For ten points, name this metropolitan city on the U.S.-Canada border in Michigan.", "answer": "<b><u>Detroit</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>Detroit</u></b> Industry Murals</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "It's not porcelain, but Parliament unintentionally increased the sale of this good following its ban on textile imports from China. Catherine de Braganza's arrival in England to marry Charles II likely made it fashionable to consume this drink daily rather than for medicinal purposes. The British East India Company's steady import of, for the point, what commodity led to its ubiquity in British culture?", "answer": "<b><u>Tea</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tea</u></b> leaves; or specific teas like Black <b><u>Tea</u></b> or Green <b><u>Tea</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1505 this man became a monk to honor a promise he made to Saint Anna after nearly being struck by lightning. This scholar discussed his daily habits in the book<em> Table</em> <em>Talk</em> and discouraged violence against feudal lords in his tract<em> Against the Murderous,</em> <em>Thieving Hordes of Peasants</em>. This theologian's stance against indulgences was laid out in a list of propositions he nailed to the door at All Saints' Church in Wittenberg [[VIT-en-berg]]. The author of the<em> Ninety-Five</em> Theses was, for the point, what seminal figure of the Reformation?", "answer": "Martin <b><u>Luther</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}